<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>blog.thesparktree.com</title>
   
   <link>https://blog.thesparktree.com</link>
   <description>Devops posts & guides about interesting tech like Docker, Letsencrypt, Chef, Angular, Automation, API's or other topics that you should know about. </description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Jason Kulatunga</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Drawbridge - SSH Config management for Jump/Bastion hosts</title>
	  <link>/drawbridge-ssh-config-management</link>
	  <author>Jason Kulatunga</author>
	  <pubDate>2018-04-30T04:19:33-05:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/drawbridge-ssh-config-management</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>In our architecture we have many environments (test/stage/prod/etc), and each environment can have one or more shards, usually broken up by datacenter/avaliablity zone (us-east-1, us-west-2, etc). Each of our shards are protected by Jump/Bastion hosts, auditing and restricting SSH access to internal components.</p>

<p>For ease of use, tunneling into bastion host protected stacks is usually done by adding entries into your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">~/.ssh/config</code> file, however when you start adding dozens of entries, it can be confusing and time consuming.</p>

<p>A while back I made a post on <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/devops/comments/8aasuw/tools_for_interacting_withmaintaining_configs_for/">/r/devops</a> asking for help finding a tool that would manage/generate ssh config files for all our jump/bastion hosts.</p>

<p>There was some interest (and great discussion), however no-one submitted a tool that solved the actual problem.</p>

<p>Since that post, I’ve worked on an open source tool that implents everything required to work with Bastion/Jump hosts efficiently as a Developer or member of Operations. Its available now on github: <a href="https://github.com/AnalogJ/drawbridge">Drawbridge</a></p>

<h2 id="here-are-some-of-its-features">Here are some of its features:</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Single binary (available for macOS and linux), only depends on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ssh</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ssh-agent</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">scp</code></li>
  <li>Uses customizable templates to ensure that Drawbridge can be used by any organization, in any configuraton</li>
  <li>Helps organize your SSH config files and PEM files</li>
  <li>Generates SSH Config files for your servers spread across multiple environments and stacks.
    <ul>
      <li>multiple ssh users/keypairs</li>
      <li>multiple environments</li>
      <li>multiple stacks per environment</li>
      <li>etc..</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Can be used to SSH directly into an internal node, routing though bastion, leveraging SSH-Agent</li>
  <li>Able to download files from internal hosts (through the jump/bastion host) using SCP syntax</li>
  <li>Supports HTTP proxy to access internal stack urls.</li>
  <li>Lists all managed config files in a heirarchy that makes sense to your organization</li>
  <li>Custom templated files can be automatically generated when a new SSH config is created.
    <ul>
      <li>eg. Chef knife.rb configs, Pac/Proxy files, etc.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Cleanup utility is built-in</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">drawbridge update</code> lets you update the binary inplace.</li>
  <li>Pretty colors. The CLI is all colorized to make it easy to skim for errors/warnings</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>You can read more &amp; download it from Github [https://github.com/AnalogJ/drawbridge]</p>

<p>I’m always open to PR’s and feature requests. I’d also love to hear any feedback you guys may have</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
