<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>blog.thesparktree.com</title>
   
   <link>https://blog.thesparktree.com</link>
   <description>Devops posts & guides about interesting tech like Docker, Letsencrypt, Chef, Angular, Automation, API's or other topics that you should know about. </description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Jason Kulatunga</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Devops for Startups & Small Teams</title>
	  <link>/devops-for-startups</link>
	  <author>Jason Kulatunga</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-09-13T04:19:33-05:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/devops-for-startups</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>When you’re working on a side-project or at a startup as part of a small focused team, it can be hard to get away from
the heads-down mentality of “just do it”. But sometimes it can be valuable to step back and recognize that a bit of upfront
infrastructure work can save you days or even weeks of time getting your MVP up and running.</p>

<p>The following are the quick and dirty Devops patterns &amp; procedures that I put in place before working on any new system.
I primarily focus on free tools and services because of how cheap I am, so feel free to replace them comparable tools of your choice,
you big spender, you.</p>

<h1 id="before-your-first-line">Before your first line</h1>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Store your code in Git</strong> - <a href="https://github.com/">Github</a> <em>[free open source]</em>/<a href="https://bitbucket.org/">Bitbucket</a>
<em>[free private]</em>/<a href="https://www.gitlab.com">GitLab</a> <em>[free private]</em>  -
there shouldn’t be more to say here other than, store your source in a VCS from day 1.</li>
  <li>Design your app with <strong>multiple environments</strong> in mind. You should be able to switch between Local/Stage/Production development
with no code changes, just configuration changes (via environmental variables or a config file). I love <a href="https://github.com/indexzero/nconf">nconf</a>
for NodeJS, but most languages have something similar.</li>
  <li><strong>Isolate your configuration.</strong> Its probably not necessary to move your configuration into a compeltely separate system yet,
but make sure you can easily if you scale. Sprinkling your configuration in multiple places is just asking for an application re-write.</li>
  <li><strong>Follow a branching pattern.</strong> At it’s simplest it could just be 2 branches, “master” and “develop” or you could go nuts
and follow <a href="http://nvie.com/posts/a-successful-git-branching-model/">gitflow</a>. It doesn’t matter, as long as you follow
the damn thing, and don’t just commit directly to master. Setup branch protection to disable commits to “master”.
This is going to be important later when you start doing Continuous Integration (CI). Bad habits are hard to break.</li>
  <li><strong>Setup CI</strong>. You don’t need to go full throttle with a standalone Jenkins server. Just make sure your code is compiling
in a clean-room environment, that doesn’t include the dozens of apps and libraries you already have installed on your
dev machine. <a href="https://travis-ci.org/">TravisCI</a> <em>[free]</em> and <a href="https://circleci.com">CircleCI</a> <em>[free]</em> are great, and integrate
with Github/Bitbucket. At a bare minimum build your artifacts inside a clean Docker container.</li>
  <li>Setup an <strong>issue tracker/project management board</strong>. <a href="https://waffle.io">Waffle.io</a> <em>[free]</em> is great and integrates with Github,
but you may be able to just get away with <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/creating-a-project-board/">Github Project Boards</a> <em>[free]</em> to start</li>
  <li>Make some Architecture decisions:
    <ul>
      <li>Decide if you can get away with a <a href="https://github.com/myles/awesome-static-generators">static frontend</a> or SPA
  architecture for your front end. If you can, you’ll get infinite scaling of your front-end for almost free.
  Distributing static files is a solved problem–CDN’s have been doing it for years. <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com">CloudFlare</a> <em>[free]</em>
  is your <del>cheapest</del> best friend. Pairing it with Github pages [free] is a poor developer’s dream.</li>
      <li>Can you go Serverless/FAAS for your backend? You no longer need to maintain or monitor hardware, you get infinite*
  scaling out of the box. The tradeoff is that your costs will vary with usage, which can be a good thing for startups.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="before-your-first-staging-environment-deploy">Before your first staging environment deploy</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Have a <strong>unit test suite</strong> - Yeah yeah, TDD. But be honest, when’s the last time you started a project with TDD? Still, you’ll thank
yourself when you come back to your code after 2 weeks, or even just a couple of days. It’s also a pre-req for some of the next points.</li>
  <li><strong>Code Coverage/Code Quality</strong> tools - When I feel that I have an application that can actually run on a server is when I
know I need to take a step back and look at all the things that I missed. Code coverage/quality tools are like a bucket of
cold water, they help stifle that feeling of euphoria that stops you from really digging into your code. A nice UI really helps
and I’m a big fan of <a href="https://coveralls.io/">Coveralls.io</a> <em>[free open source]</em> and <a href="https://codecov.io/">CodeCov</a> <em>[free open source]</em>,
both have great integration with SCM’s and CI platforms.</li>
  <li><strong>Forward your logs</strong> to a centralized logging system (Cloud-watch is fine, if you don’t plan on actually debugging your app.)
<a href="https://www.loggly.com">Loggly</a> <em>[free]</em> is great. Make sure you forward environment data and user data to your log aggregator as well, to give your
logs context.</li>
  <li><strong>Use a CDN</strong> like <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com">CloudFlare</a> <em>[free]</em> in front of your site if you haven’t already. You definitely don’t have the traffic yet
that requires it, but don’t wait until you’re ready to launch. Its time-consuming, error prone and can cause DNS downtime,
even if you don’t misconfigure something. It’s not something you want to leave to the last minute.</li>
  <li><strong>Write documentation/setup instructions</strong> as you start building your Stage environment. Your documentation should always
be relative to Stage, <strong>NOT</strong> Production. You will forget. You will copy and paste from your docs, and you will run a
destructive operation against your production database. <a href="https://np.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions/comments/6ez8ag/accidentally_destroyed_production_database_on/">Cough..</a>
    <ul>
      <li>List all the weird/one-off configuration you had to do to get your staging server working. New accounts on 3rd
  party services, ip whitelisting, database population, you’ll need this checklist when you spin up Production, and
  finding out whats different between Prod and Stage is going to be a huge pain without it. Infrastructure-as-code/Configuration Management
   is your friend here, but may not be enough by itself.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Follow modern infrastructure practices.</strong> <a href="https://www.terraform.io/">Infrastructure-as-code</a> and <a href="https://www.chef.io/chef/">Configuration</a> <a href="https://puppet.com/">Management</a> are buzzwords for a reason.
And they don’t have to be super complicated. You don’t need to design the Mona Lisa of Chef cookbooks. At a bare minimum
make sure that you can spin up a whole environment with the click of a single button. Automation is the key here. You’ll
be doing this a lot more than you’d expect, so take some time and do it right. When you find yourself under the gun, needing
to scale your environment, you’ll be thankful.</li>
  <li><strong>Version your code.</strong> Create releases, tag your software, its incredibly useful when debugging what software your actually
running in different environments. It also makes it much easier to deploy previous versions when you want to do regression
testing, or rollback a broken deployment. Check out something like <a href="https://github.com/AnalogJ/capsulecd">CapsuleCD</a>
which can build, test, tag, merge branches and release your software automatically.</li>
  <li><strong>Setup Continuous Deployments</strong> - If you’re already using a CI platform to test your code, why not automatically deploy your
validated code to your Staging environment? Depending on your application architecture, this may be a bit complicated, but
having your CI tested code deployed to a staging environment automatically is going to drastically improve your development
cadence while still ensuring stability. And if your stability is being effected, prioritize your tests, they’re supposed to
catch 90% of your errors before they even get to a staging env.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="before-your-first-prod-deploy">Before your first prod deploy</h1>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Automate your backups.</strong> This is probably obvious to everyone, but a backup process without a verified restore process is
useless. Try to setup a weekly backup and restore of your staging environment database. Use the same code/process you would in Production.</li>
  <li>Write a script to <strong>populate your database</strong> with test data. Massive amounts of test data. <a href="https://github.com/marak/Faker.js/">Faker.js</a>
has an API. Check how your Staging environment actually handles real data, not just the toy amounts you’ve thrown in.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="once-your-application-is-live">Once your application is live</h1>
<ul>
  <li>Track the versions of your <strong>application’s dependencies, and their dependencies</strong>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turtles_all_the_way_down">it’s turtles all the way down</a>. This is to ensure that you know
what software makes up your stack, but also so you can be notified of bug fixes and security issues.</li>
  <li>Make sure you have <strong>monitoring</strong> in place.
    <ul>
      <li><a href="https://www.pingdom.com/free">Pingdom</a> <em>[free]</em> will let notify you if your application is inaccessible externally.</li>
      <li>Track system metrics like CPU and memory load on your servers. <a href="https://newrelic.com/">NewRelic</a> <em>[free]</em>,
  <a href="https://www.librato.com/">Librato</a> <em>[free]</em> and <a href="https://cloud.google.com/stackdriver/">StackDriver</a> <em>[paid]</em> work well.</li>
      <li>Configure a user analytics &amp; monitoring solution like <a href="https://www.google.com/analytics/">Google Analytics</a> <em>[free]</em>. Setup alerts when your traffic
  increases or drops more than 15%.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>This is just my checklist, but I’d love to hear yours. Is there any devopsy related tasks you think I’m missing?</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>CapsuleCD v2 Released</title>
	  <link>/capsulecd-v2-released</link>
	  <author>Jason Kulatunga</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-08-06T04:19:33-05:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/capsulecd-v2-released</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><a href="https://github.com/AnalogJ/capsulecd">CapsuleCD</a> is made up of a series of scripts/commands that
make it easy for you to package and release a new version of your library artifact (Ruby gem, Npm package, Chef cookbook.. ) while still following best practices:</p>

<ul>
  <li>bumping <code class="highlighter-rouge">semvar</code> tags</li>
  <li>regenerating any <code class="highlighter-rouge">*.lock</code> files</li>
  <li>validates all dependencies exist and are free of vulnerabilities</li>
  <li>runs unit tests &amp; linters</li>
  <li>uploads versioned artifact to community hosting service (rubygems/supermarket/pypi/etc)</li>
  <li>creating a new git tag</li>
  <li>pushing changes back to source control &amp; creating a release</li>
  <li>and others..</li>
</ul>

<p>While <code class="highlighter-rouge">CapsuleCD</code> <strong>was</strong> a series of scripts, with the release of <strong>v2</strong> that’s no longer the case.</p>

<p><code class="highlighter-rouge">CapsuleCD</code> has been re-written, and is now available as a <a href="https://github.com/AnalogJ/capsulecd/releases">static binary</a>
on <a href="https://github.com/AnalogJ/capsulecd/releases/download/v2.0.10/capsulecd-darwin-amd64"><code class="highlighter-rouge">macOS</code></a> and
<a href="https://github.com/AnalogJ/capsulecd/releases/download/v2.0.10/capsulecd-linux-amd64"><code class="highlighter-rouge">Linux</code></a>
(<code class="highlighter-rouge">Windows</code> and <code class="highlighter-rouge">NuGet</code> support is hopefully coming soon)</p>

<p>You no longer need to worry that the version of Ruby used by your library &amp; <code class="highlighter-rouge">gemspec</code> is different than the
version required by <code class="highlighter-rouge">CapsuleCD</code>. If you maintain any Python or NodeJS libraries, this also means that a Ruby
runtime for just for CapsuleCD is unnecessary. The <code class="highlighter-rouge">CapsuleCD</code> <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/analogj/capsulecd/tags/">Docker</a>
images for other languages are much slimmer, and based off the standard community images with <a href="https://github.com/AnalogJ/capsulecd-docker">minimal changes</a>.</p>

<p>Releasing a new version of your Ruby library hasn’t changed, it’s as easy as downloading the <a href="https://github.com/AnalogJ/capsulecd/releases">binary</a> and running:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>CAPSULE_SCM_GITHUB_ACCESS_TOKEN=123456789ABCDEF \
CAPSULE_SCM_REPO_FULL_NAME=AnalogJ/gem_analogj_test \
CAPSULE_SCM_PULL_REQUEST=4 \
CAPSULE_RUBYGEMS_API_KEY=ASDF12345F \
capsulecd start --scm github --package_type ruby
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>Click below to watch a screencast of <code class="highlighter-rouge">CapuleCD</code> in action:</p>

<p align="center">
<a href="https://analogj.github.io/capsulecd">
  <img alt="CapsuleCD screencast" width="800" src="https://cdn.rawgit.com/AnalogJ/capsulecd/v2.0.10/capsulecd-screencast.png" />
  </a>
</p>

<div class="github-widget" data-repo="AnalogJ/capsulecd"></div>


	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>15 Lessons in Golang</title>
	  <link>/15-lessons-in-golang</link>
	  <author>Jason Kulatunga</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-07-31T04:19:33-05:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/15-lessons-in-golang</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Like many developers, I heard a lot of buzz about Golang (or is it Go, I’m still not sure).
In case you’re not familiar with it, it’s an open source language developed by Google.
It mostly caught my interest due to the fact that it’s pitched as a statically typed, compiled modern language.</p>

<p>For a long time that was the extent of my Golang knowledge. I knew I wanted to take a closer look at
it at some point, but I had other priorities. About 4 months ago, I realized the Golang could be the
solution to one of the problems I was facing with <a href="https://github.com/AnalogJ/capsulecd">CapsuleCD</a>, my application for generically automating
package releases for any language (npm, cookbooks, gems, pip, jars, etc).</p>

<div class="github-widget" data-repo="AnalogJ/capsulecd"></div>

<p>The problem was that <a href="https://github.com/AnalogJ/capsulecd">CapsuleCD</a> was a executable distributed in a Ruby gem, which meant that anyone
who wanted to use <code class="highlighter-rouge">CapsuleCD</code> needed to have a Ruby interpreter installed on their build machine, even
if all they were just trying to do was package a Python library. This made my Docker containers bloated,
and more complicated to develop. Wouldn’t it be nice to just have single binary I could download into the
container? And so the migration to Golang began, if only in my head at that point.</p>

<p>Over the next couple months, I kept going back to that idea, and a couple weeks ago, I finally sat down and
started porting my ~3000 line Ruby application to Golang. While I could have just bought a book like Golang
for Dummies, I decided to just jump into the coding, and just read blog posts and stack overflow when I got stuck.</p>

<p>I can already hear some of you cringing. To be honest, while I was having a lot of fun, my initial development
was pretty slow. I was trying to write an application in a new language, without knowing any of the conventions.
The thing is, I loved it. Those “Ah-Ha!” moments and getting things compiling again after a huge refactor
were an incredible motivator.</p>

<p>Here’s a bunch of the unexpected/unconventional things I learned while porting my app to Golang.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Please note, these are things that I didn’t <strong>expect</strong> when I started writing Golang code with a
background in popular typed and dynamically typed languages, (C++, C#, Java, Ruby, Python and NodeJS).
These are not necessarily criticisms of Golang. I was able to go from 0 -&gt; working release of my software
in a completely new language in 2 weeks. That’s pretty awesome if you ask me.</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="before-your-first-line">Before your first line.</h1>

<h2 id="package-layout">Package Layout</h2>
<p>While not required for a compiled language, I was still unprepared for the fact that there doesn’t seem to be a <strong>Standard™</strong> folder structure for a Golang library, like there is for Ruby, Chef &amp; Node. There seem to be a couple of popular community structures, and I found myself liking <a href="https://peter.bourgon.org/go-best-practices-2016/#repository-structure">Peter Bourgon’s recommendations</a>.</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>github.com/peterbourgon/foo/
  circle.yml
  Dockerfile
  cmd/
    foosrv/
      main.go
    foocli/
      main.go
  pkg/
    fs/
      fs.go
      fs_test.go
      mock.go
      mock_test.go
    merge/
      merge.go
      merge_test.go
    api/
      api.go
      api_test.go
</code></pre>
</div>

<h2 id="circular-dependencies">!Circular Dependencies</h2>
<p>Package layout becomes even more important when you find out that Golang does’t support circular
dependencies between packages. If A imports B, and B imports A, Golang will give up and complain.
I actually kinda like it, as it forced me to think a bit more about my application’s domain model.</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>import cycle not allowed
package github.com/AnalogJ/dep/a
  imports github.com/AnalogJ/dep/b
  imports github.com/AnalogJ/dep/a
</code></pre>
</div>

<h2 id="dependency-management">Dependency management</h2>
<p><code class="highlighter-rouge">npm</code>, <code class="highlighter-rouge">pypi</code>, <code class="highlighter-rouge">bundler</code>. Each of these package managers are synonymous with their language. However Golang
doesn’t have an official package manger (<a href="https://github.com/golang/dep">yet</a>). In the meantime the community
has come up with a <a href="https://github.com/Masterminds/glide">couple</a> <a href="https://github.com/FiloSottile/gvt">of</a>
<a href="https://github.com/kardianos/govendor">good</a> <a href="https://github.com/FiloSottile/gvt">alternatives</a>. The problem
is that they are all really good, and it can be a bit daunting to pick one. I ended up choosing <a href="https://github.com/Masterminds/glide">Glide</a>,
because it has a similar feel to <code class="highlighter-rouge">bundler</code> and <code class="highlighter-rouge">npm</code>.</p>

<h2 id="documentation">Documentation</h2>
<p>This is actually one of the best things about Golang. <code class="highlighter-rouge">go docs</code> and the <code class="highlighter-rouge">godoc.org</code> site are awesome
and standardize the documentation for any library you might use. This is a nice step up from the NodeJS
community where all package documentation is custom and self hosted.</p>

<h2 id="goroot-gopath">GOROOT, GOPATH</h2>
<p>Golang imports are done in a kind of weird way. Unlike most other languages, Golang basically requires
that your source live in pre-configured folder(s). I’m not going to delve into the details, but you should
know that it takes a bit of setup &amp; getting used to. Dmitri Shuralyov’s <a href="https://dmitri.shuralyov.com/blog/18">How I use GOPATH with multiple
workspaces</a> is a great resource.</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>GOPATH=/landing/workspace/path:/personal/workspace/path:/corporate/workspace/path
</code></pre>
</div>

<h1 id="scratching-that-itch">Scratching that Itch.</h1>

<h2 id="pseudo-class-struct-inheritance">Pseudo <del>Class</del> Struct Inheritance</h2>
<p>The Golang developers did some interesting things when designing the inheritance model. Instead of using
one of the more conventional inheritance models of typed languages like multiple-inheritance or classical
inheritance, Golang follows a multiple composition pattern similar to Ruby.
<a href="https://github.com/luciotato/golang-notes/blob/master/OOP.md#method-shadowing">Method-Shadowing</a> can
cause some unexpected results if not understood completely.</p>

<h2 id="duck-typed-interfaces">Duck-Typed Interfaces</h2>
<p>This is another cool unexpected feature of Golang. Interfaces are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duck_typing">duck-typed</a>,
something I’ve only seen in dynamically typed languages. This duck-typing works hand-in-hand with <code class="highlighter-rouge">struct</code>
composition.</p>

<h2 id="structs-have-fields-interfaces-dont">Structs have fields, Interfaces don’t</h2>
<p>Unfortunately <code class="highlighter-rouge">structs</code> can’t have the same <em>API</em> as <code class="highlighter-rouge">interfaces</code>, as the latter cannot define fields. This
is not a huge issue, as one can just define a getter and a setter method on the interface, but it was a bit
confusing. I’m sure theres a good technical/CS theory answer for why this is, but yeah.</p>

<h2 id="publicprivate-naming">Public/Private naming</h2>
<p>Golang took Python’s <code class="highlighter-rouge">public</code> and <code class="highlighter-rouge">private</code> method naming scheme one level further. When I initially found
out that functions, methods and struct names starting with an uppercase character are public and lowercase
are private, I wasn’t sure how to feel about it. But honestly, after working with Golang for 2 weeks, I
really like this convention.</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>type PublicStructName struct {}
type privateStructName struct {}
</code></pre>
</div>

<h2 id="defer">defer</h2>
<p>Another surprisingly useful feature Golang. I’m sure it’s a result of Golang’s parallel processing and
error model, but <code class="highlighter-rouge">defer</code>’s make it really easy to keep your cleanup close to the originating code. Mentally
I treat it like an alternative to a <code class="highlighter-rouge">finally</code> method in the <code class="highlighter-rouge">try-catch-finally</code> pattern or the <code class="highlighter-rouge">using</code>
block in <code class="highlighter-rouge">C#</code>/<code class="highlighter-rouge">Java</code> but I’m sure there are more creative uses for it.</p>

<h2 id="go-fmt-is-awesome"><code class="highlighter-rouge">go fmt</code> is awesome</h2>
<p>You’ll never have the “tabs vs spaces” debate with a Golang developer. There is a standardized Golang
style and <code class="highlighter-rouge">go fmt</code> can reformat your code to comply with it. It’s a neat tool, and reading its source
introduced me to the powerful <a href="https://golang.org/pkg/go/parser/"><code class="highlighter-rouge">parser</code></a> and <a href="https://golang.org/pkg/go/ast/"><code class="highlighter-rouge">ast</code></a> libraries.</p>

<h2 id="goarch-goos-cgo--cross-compiling">GOARCH, GOOS, CGO &amp; Cross Compiling</h2>
<p>My goal of creating a single standalone <code class="highlighter-rouge">CapsuleCD</code> binary is the entire reason I started my port
to Golang. However it quickly became apparent that simple static binaries aren’t an intrinsic feature
of Golang (which should have been obvious). If your code is all written in vanilla Golang, and the code
of all your dependencies (and their dependencies), then you can <a href="http://golangcookbook.com/chapters/running/cross-compiling/">build static binaries</a>
to your heart’s content using <code class="highlighter-rouge">GOOS</code> and <code class="highlighter-rouge">GOARCH</code>. However if you’re unlucky like I was, and you have
a dependency that calls <code class="highlighter-rouge">C</code> code under the hood (by importing a <code class="highlighter-rouge">C pseudo-package</code>) then you’re in for
a world of pain. Don’t get me wrong, creating a dynamically linked binary is still super easy. But to
generate a static binary, with no external dependencies, means you need to ensure that all your
<code class="highlighter-rouge">C</code> dependencies (and their dependencies) are all statically linked too. Like I said, obvious.
<code class="highlighter-rouge">C pseudo-packages</code> are compiled via <code class="highlighter-rouge">CGO</code>, and you’ll need to look at the documentation to find all
the compiler flags necessary to help <code class="highlighter-rouge">CGO</code> locate your static libraries. A table of all supported GOOS
and GOARCH pairs is located in the <a href="https://golang.org/doc/install/source#environment">Golang docs</a></p>

<h1 id="how-do-i-test-this">How do I test this?</h1>

<h2 id="hidden-in-plain-sight">Hidden in plain sight</h2>
<p>Test files are suffixed with <code class="highlighter-rouge">_test.go</code> and should be located side-by-side with the code they test,
rather than relegated to a special testing folder. Its nice, even though it feels a bit cluttered at first.</p>

<p>Test data goes in a special <code class="highlighter-rouge">testdata</code> folder. Both the <code class="highlighter-rouge">testdata</code> folder and <code class="highlighter-rouge">_test.go</code> files are completely
ignored by the compiler during <code class="highlighter-rouge">go build</code>.</p>

<h2 id="go-list-and-vendor-folder"><code class="highlighter-rouge">go list</code> and <code class="highlighter-rouge">vendor</code> folder</h2>
<p>So, dependency management is pretty new to the Golang language, and not all tools understand the special
<code class="highlighter-rouge">vendor</code> folder. As such, when you run <code class="highlighter-rouge">go test</code>, by default you’ll find it running the tests of all your
dependencies. Use <code class="highlighter-rouge">go list | grep -v /vendor</code> to get Golang to ignore the vendor folder.</p>

<p><code class="highlighter-rouge">go fmt $(go list ./... | grep -v /vendor/)</code></p>

<h2 id="if-err--nil"><code class="highlighter-rouge">if err != nil</code></h2>
<p>I’m a stickler for code coverage. I try to keep my open source projects above 80% coverage, but I’m having
a hard time doing that with Golang. Those of you already familiar with Golang will probably just point out that
Golang is one of the easiest languages to get <a href="https://blog.golang.org/cover">good coverage in</a>. Rather
than creating a seperate execution path for errors (<code class="highlighter-rouge">try-catch-finally</code>) Golang treats all errors as standard objects.
Golang convention states that functions which can produce errors should return them as it’s last <code class="highlighter-rouge">return</code> argument.</p>

<p>It’s a pretty interesting model, which reminds me a bit of <code class="highlighter-rouge">Node</code>’s built-in functions. However, just like <code class="highlighter-rouge">Node</code>, it can
be difficult to write unit tests that produce errors in built-in functionality. This becomes even more annoying when you follow
a coding pattern where you bubble-up errors, and then handle them at a higher level. When doing this, you’ll write alot of
code the looks like the following:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>data, err := myfunction(...)
if(err != nil){
	return err
}

data2, err2 := myfunction2(...)
if(err2 != nil){
	return err
}

</code></pre>
</div>

<p>This starts to clutter up your code pretty quick. At this point some of you may be thinking that <code class="highlighter-rouge">interface</code>s and <code class="highlighter-rouge">mock</code>s
would solve these problems. While that’s true in some cases, I don’t think it makes sense to write massive <code class="highlighter-rouge">interface</code>s for
built-in libraries like <code class="highlighter-rouge">os</code> and <code class="highlighter-rouge">ioutil</code>, or pass those libraries in as arguments, just so that we can artifically generate
errors for <code class="highlighter-rouge">ioutil.WriteFile</code> and <code class="highlighter-rouge">os.MkdirAll</code>.</p>

<p>I’m that this is definitely a shortcoming in my mental-model, but I’ve read a ton of documentation and blog posts on how
unit tests and code coverage should be done in Golang, and I still haven’t found a pattern that makes sense without
seeming to require a dependency injection engine of some sort, something that Golang seems to actively dislike as too cumbersome.</p>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>

<p>I’d love to hear your thoughts. I’ve only been working with Golang for a few weeks, but it’s been an incredibly educational
and enjoyable experience. I was able to go from no experience to building a real, working application in Golang in very
little time, not just toy examples from some book. I know that I’m no expert in Golang yet, and that there are still  theory gaps
in my understanding of Golang, but I feel like they are much further apart than I expected when I went down this <code class="highlighter-rouge">self-taught without books</code> path.</p>

<p>Golang worked exactly as I thought it would, giving me <a href="https://github.com/AnalogJ/capsulecd/releases">binaries</a> that I can easily download
onto slim Docker containers, without requiring a Ruby interpreter. If you maintain executables in other languages, I would
definitely recommend you consider giving Golang a try.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
